Guide to the George Van Santvoord Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Van Santvoord collection
1914-1989
YCAL MSS 763
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.84
(9 boxes) + 2 art
The George Van Santvoord collection was formed by Van Santvoord's relatives, friends and associates. Various early acquisitions include manuscript material by Van Santvoord and others, correspondence, and printed material. Sketchbooks contain original ink and pencil sketches and watercolors, with views of places visited by Van Santvoord in South Africa, the Far East, Panama Canal, Galapagos, Marquesas, Bora Bora, Tahiti, Fiji, Borneo, and elsewhere. The July 1985 Acquisition contains correspondence, including letters from Van Santvoord to his father Seymour, dating from 1914 to 1918, and letters to Van Santvoord from Lancelot Ridley Phelps, William Lyon Phelps, Harris Rackham, and others. The October 1995 Acquisition contains manuscript notes relating to John Milton and the seventeeth century, additional correspondence, material relating to Yale University, dating largely from the 1940s, and other personal papers.
Van Santvoord, George, 1891-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
George Van Santvoord (1891-1975)
George Van Santvoord was born in Bennington, Vermont on 5 August, 1891 and educated at Hotchkiss School, Yale University (1912), and Oxford Univeristy. After serving with the American Field Service and 39th U.S. Infantry, Van Santvoord taught English at Yale (1919-1921) and at the University of Buffalo (1922-1925). Van Santvoord then returned to Hotchkiss School, a preparatory school in Lakeville, Connecticut, to serve as Headmaster, a post he held from 1926 to 1955. Upon his retirement, he served in the Vermont legislature for ten years. Van Santvoord died in Williamstown, Massachusetts on 19 Februrary 1975.
Scope and Contents
The George Van Santvoord collection was formed by Mr. Van Santvoord's relatives, friends and associates. Various early acquisitions include manuscript material by Van Santvoord and others, correspondence, and printed material. Sketchbooks contain original ink and pencil sketches and watercolors, with views of places visited by Van Santvoord in South Africa, the Far East, Panama Canal, Galapagos, Marquesas, Bora Bora, Tahiti, Fiji, Borneo, and elsewhere. The July 1985 Acquisition contains correspondence, including letters from Van Santvoord to his father Seymour, dating from 1914 to 1918, and letters to Van Santvoord from Lancelot Ridley Phelps, William Lyon Phelps, Harris Rackham, and others. The October 1995 Acquisition contains manuscript notes relating to John Milton and the seventeenth century, additional correspondence, material relating to Yale University, dating largely from the 1940s, and other personal papers.
Arrangement
Organized into five groupings: Early Acquisitions, July 1985 Acquisition, January 1989 Acquisition, November 1990 Acquisition, and October 1995 Acquisition.
Bora-Bora (French Polynesia) -- Description and travel; Borneo -- Description and travel; Fiji -- Description and travel; Galapagos Islands -- Description and travel; Marquesas Islands (French Polynesia) -- Description and travel; Panama Canal (Panama) -- Description and travel; South Africa -- Description and travel; Tahiti (French Polynesia: Island) -- Description and travel; Sketches; Watercolors (paintings); Phelps, Lancelot Ridley, 1853-1936; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Rackham, H. (Harris), 1868-1944; Van Santvoord, George, 1891-1975; Van Santvoord, Seymour, 1858-1938; Hotchkiss School; Yale University
- Early Acquisitions, 1929-1989; 0.8; (4 boxes) + 2 art
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subdivisions: Manuscripts, Correspondence, and Printed Material.
  Scope and Contents
  Early Acquisitions include manuscript material by Van Santvoord and others, correspondence, and printed material. Sketchbooks contain original pencil and ink sketches and watercolors, with views of places visited by Van Santvoord while on a tour, including South Africa, the Far East, Panama Canal, Galapagos, Marquesas, Bora Bora, Tahiti, Fiji, Borneo, and elsewhere.
  Former call number: Za Van Santvoord.
  Acquired from various sources. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Manuscripts
    - Manuscripts by George Van Santvoord
      - "Bird's Eye Views From the Bergensfjord," sketchbook, 1964 (Box 1)
      - "Caronia, 1956," sketchbook
      - Letters by George Van Santvoord, 1978-1979; 2 (Box 1)
        Contains transcriptions, typescript, of letters dated from 1930 to 1975, edited and compiled by Chingis Guirey
      - "Russian Rhymes," poems, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1)
      - "Some New Tales of The South Pacific," sketches 1-8, 1958 (Box 4 (Art))
      - "Some New Tales of The South Pacific," sketches 9-17, 1958 (Box 5 (Art))
    - Manuscripts by Others
      - Blanchard, Brand
        - "In Memoriam: George Van Santvoord (1891-1978)," typescript, corrected, 1975 (Box 1)
      - Hughes, R.D.
        - "For G.V.S., an Epitaph," poem, typescript (photocopy), [1975?] (Box 1)
      - Unidentified
        - List of pies, autograph manuscript, addressed to "Mrs. Seymour Van Santvoord", undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - George Van Santvoord Correspondence
      - Alumnae Association of The Hotchkiss School, 1955 May (Box 1)
      - Bainbridge, John S., 1932-1972 (Box 1)
      - Beal, John Wilkie, 1965-1978, undated; 2 (Box 1)
      - Blagden, Thomas P., 1962-1974 (Box 1)
      - Bowen, John G., 1956-1975, undated; 3 (Box 1)
      - Bradley, Edward M., 1951 July 25 (Box 1)
      - Shouse, Martha, 1974 (Box 1)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
    - Third-Party Correspondence
      - Beal, John Wilkie, 1974-1980 (Box 1)
        Includes correspondence with James T. Cleland, Chingis Guirey, The Hotchkiss School, Agnes Rice, Richard Severo, Potter Stewart, and Amos and Catherine Wilder
      - Bowen, John G., 1974 (Box 1)
        Includes correspondence with Martha Shouse
      - Guirey, Chingis, 1978-1989, undated (Box 1)
        Includes correspondence with John Wilkie Beal, Oriel College, Oxford, Agnes Rice, and Frank Sproule
  - Printed Material
    - Certificates and awards, 1929-1961
    - Clippings, 1962-1975, undated (Box 2)
    - Eulogy of the Life, Character and Services of Andrew Jackson, by Geoge Van Santvoord, printed version, circa 1945 (Box 2)
    - "Furnace Grove 1858-1958: The Story of a Family Home", undated (Box 2)
    - "George Van Santvoord" by A. William Olsen, printed version, Hotchkiss Alumni Magazine, 1975 (Box 2)
    - "George Van Santvoord: After Hotchkiss--Return to Vermont" by James S. Holden, printed version, Hotchkiss Alumni Magazine, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "George Van Santvoord Memorial Service," printed version, The Hotchkiss Record, 1975 May 17
    - "In Memoriam: George Van Santvoord, 1891-1975", 1975 May 17 (Box 2)
    - Invitation to Hotchkiss School Alumni, 1955 April 22 (Box 2)
    - The poetry of George Van Santvoord: Annotated by John Wilkie Beal (two copies), circa 1977; 2 (Box 2)
  - Oversize
    - "Caronia, 1956," sketchbook (Box 3)
    - Certificates and awards, 1929-1961 (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Clippings, 1962-1975, undated (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - "George Van Santvoord Memorial Service," printed version, The Hotchkiss Record, 1975 May 17 (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - State of Vermont Joint Resolution Memorializing George Van Santvoord, 1975 (Box 6 (Oversize))
- July 1985 Acquisition, 1914-1919; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by letter general folders and correspondent.
  The July 1985 Acquisition contains correspondence, including letters from Van Santvoord to his father Seymour, dating from 1914 to 1918, and letters to Van Santvoord from Lancelot Ridley Phelps, William Lyon Phelps, Harris Rackham, and others.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 337.
  Gift of John G. Bowen, 1985.
  - "A" - "G" general, 1915-1918, undated (Box 7)
  - "H" - "Z" general, 1916-1919, undated (Box 7)
  - Scott, C. A., 1916-1919, undated (Box 7)
  - Van Santvoord, Seymour, 1914-1918, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - ----, Fred, 1916-1917, undated (Box 7)
  - Unidentified, 1916, undated (Box 7)
  - Third-party letters, 1916-1918 (Box 7)
- January 1989 Acquisition, 1918-1942; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by letter general folder and name.
  The January 1989 Acquisition contains additional correspondence.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 87.
  Gift of John G. Bowen, 1989.
  - "B" general, 1939-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "C" general, 1939-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "D" general, 1939 (Box 8)
  - "E" general, undated (Box 8)
  - "F" general, 1940, undated (Box 8)
  - "G" general, 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - "H" general, 1939-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "K" general, 1940-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "L" general, 1941-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "M" general, 1940-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - New Haven Boys' Club, 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - "O" general, 1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "P" general, 1940-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "R" general, 1940, undated (Box 8)
  - "S" general, 1939-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - "T" general, 1940 April 5 (Box 8)
  - [Van Santvoord?], Alice Louise, undated (Box 8)
  - [Van Santvoord?], Ted, 1940, undated (Box 8)
  - Walker, Cooper, 1939-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1918-1942, undated; 4 (Box 8)
  - Unidentified family, undated (Box 8)
- November 1990 Acquisition, 1972 August 22
  The November 1990 Acquisition contains a single autograph letter, signed, from George Van Santvoord to "Jack" expressing gratitude for a letter.
  Former call number: Uncat Za File 253.
  Gift of John G. Bowen, 1990.
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Van Santvoord to "Jack", 1972 August 22 (Box 8)
- October 1995 Acquisition, 1925-1950; 1.42; (3 boxes)
  Files not arranged in any particular order.
  The October 1995 Acquisition contains manuscript notes relating to John Milton and the seventeenth century, correspondence, papers relating to Van Santvoord's involvement with Yale University, dating largely from the 1940s, and other personal papers. The Yale University material includes documentation from an Educational Policy Committee, Finance Committee, the Yale Corporation, and other offices.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 456.
  Gift of The Hotchkiss School, 1995.
  - Lascelles Abercrombie, notes, autograph, undated (Box 9)
  - Material relating to Milton and the 17th century, 1926, undated; 13 (Box 9)
  - Oxford University Press correspondence and proofs, 1925-1926, undated (Box 9)
  - "A" general, 1936 December 16 (Box 9)
  - "B" general, 1936-1938, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - "C" - "D" general, 1936-1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "D" general, 1936, undated (Box 9)
  - "E" - "F" general, 1937-1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "G" general, 1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "H" general, 1934-1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "J" - "L" general, 1937-1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "M" general, 1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "N" - "O" general, 1935-1937, undated (Box 9)
  - "P" general, 1936-1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "R" general, 1937-1938, undated (Box 9)
  - "S" - "T" general, 1936-1937, undated (Box 9)
  - "U" - "V" general, 1934-1936, undated (Box 9)
  - "W" general, 1933-1938, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1927-1936, undated (Box 9)
  - Yale University material, 1939-1940, undated; 6 (Box 9)
  - Yale University material, 1939-1947, undated; 23 (Box 10)
  - Yale University material, 1950 (Box 11)
  - Emma Willard School material, 1940, undated (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1940-1942, undated (Box 11)